Candlestick patterns are one of the main
ways professional Traders enter the
market so if you don't have an effective
Candlestick pattern you can use for
entries then it could be a main reason
that you're not quite profitable yet so
whether you are a complete beginner or
just someone who's been struggling with
your trading for a while by the end of
this video you will be able to quickly
and easily spot a very effective
Candlestick pattern this Candlestick
pattern has helped me win a large number
of Trades over the past few years and is
a pattern I use to this day in my own
trading so right after the intro and
disclaimer I'm gonna give you every rule
to this pattern so you too will have an
effective Candlestick pattern to use
anytime you want to place a trade so if
that sounds good go ahead and click that
like button for me go ahead and
subscribe if you are new
[Music]
thank you
welcome back and just in case you're
brand new my name is Steven I've been
trading for a little over a decade and
on this channel I share all my trading
skills that I've learned throughout my
trading career in order to try to help
you become a better Trader so let's
first take a look at the bearish version
of this Candlestick pattern you're going
to be learning today the bearish version
of this Candlestick pattern is something
I call the s-h-e-c
s-h-e-c stands for swing eye engulfing
candle let's break down the first part
of this swing high this means that this
Candlestick pattern can only occur at
the swing high of an overall trend let's
say Trends are pushing up I need to see
this at the swing I or the highest die
of a trend or at the swing high of a
pullback what that would look like is
prices are moving down it would have to
be the highest Candlestick of a
particular pullback that would be the
swing high of the pullback so that's the
first step in understanding this
Candlestick pattern and the anatomy of
it next up we have engulfing candle in
case you don't know what an engulfing
candle is essentially it is when we have
a candle that is a color change candle
meaning we went from green to Red in a
bearish version of this and the body of
the red candle is larger than the body
of the green candle if those two rules
are met we have what is called an
engulfing candle in Forex that engulfing
candle will normally start at the same
exact place as the previous candle in
stocks you want to see this candle start
a little bit above it for this swing
High engulfing candle so to give you an
idea of what we could see and the way we
could use this pattern if prices were
trending higher and we had let's say RSI
Divergence which we'll talk about in
just a second and let's say we were at a
major level of structure that might be a
time I decide to use a Candlestick
pattern like the swing High engulfing
pattern in order to enter a trade it
gives you a good place to enter and
again it's been effective for me over
the years at proving to be profitable
along with that it gives you a very easy
place to put your stop loss above the
swing high of this swing High engulfing
candle and in the opposite direction we
can use this even if we're trending down
as long as it is the top of a pullback
so that would look something like this
markets are trending down and then this
becomes the top of the pullback before
the trend continuation in that downtrend
so before we take a look at a bullish
version of this let's go to some charts
I'll show you a live trade I'm in right
now using this exact Candlestick pattern
along with the full breakdown of that
trade so you can understand how I use
this Candlestick pattern in combination
with full strategies so let's go take a
look at that right now this trade was on
the Euro Canada and I'm going to break
it down completely right now so let's go
ahead and take a look at the Candlestick
pattern tell me when you spot it in the
comments section or just say it out loud
whenever you spot the actual pattern
itself does that look familiar where
price is right now I'll zoom in a bit do
we have what I would identify as a swing
High engulfing again well what are the
rules we need it to be the swinger which
is the highest I in Trend or the highest
high in a pullback is that the case here
yes this High the red candle we see is
in fact the swing high of the overall
trend so far is it an engulfing candle
well is the red body bigger than the
green body that answer is yes so this is
the actual Candlestick pattern that we
entered on now let me break down the
rest of the things that I'd like to
combine with this swing High engulfing
candle in order to turn it into a full
strategy because as hopefully you
already know if you don't no Candlestick
pattern is going to be some type of Holy
Grail you're going to have to combine
different technical factors in order to
ever come up with a profitable trading
strategy so a Candlestick pattern is
never going to be the secret the only
thing this Candlestick pattern does is
that when we have other conditions met
like prices being at previous structure
like RSI Divergence it gives us an edge
and a rules based way to place a trade
which is very important a lot of Traders
try to place trades with random entry
reasons all the time and that equals
very inconsistent results whereas if you
place trades in a consistent way with an
effective pattern and with an easy place
to put your stop loss that can help you
turn a non-profitable strategy into a
profitable strategy so in this case we
had our engulfing candle happen and on
top of that if I zoom out to the daily
chart and we scroll left a bit you can
see that this swing High engulfing
pattern was happening at a major level
of resistance so that's already step
number one and if you don't know yet I
create strategies based on something
called c e s t we have our conditions
followed by our entry followed by stops
and followed by targets so the
conditions here are we have a major
level of structure on the daily chart
the other condition that I really like
to see but isn't completely necessary is
RSI Divergence on either time frame this
RSI Divergence can be happening here on
the daily chart which we do have and or
on the four hour chart which we'll look
at in a second so RSI Divergence means
that prices are creating higher highs
while your RSI indicator is creating
equal or lower highs in this case we
have equal highs on the RSI indicator
whilst getting higher highs on price I
am nearly positive I just use the word
whilst and I don't even know what that
means so while getting higher highs on
price lower eyes on the RSI indicator
man it's hard to believe English is my
first language dropping down now though
to the four hour chart as you can see
here on the RSI indicator we do in fact
have what looks to be equal highs what
is price doing creating higher highs so
in this case whenever we're looking at
this from a strategy standpoint a
rules-based strategy which is what you
need especially at the beginning or if
you're struggling in order to become
profitable and consistent if we look at
this from a rules-based strategy
standpoint we have the condition of the
daily daily
major structure my voice is not working
today at all we have the condition of
RSI Divergence
and now after having those two things
the only thing I'm looking for next is
going to be my entry now the whole
purpose of this video is to teach you
this entry pattern that is our swing
High engulfing pattern so we obviously
have that entry for a stop loss like I
already said I like to put the stop loss
right above the previous odd the swing
High engulfing candle so my stop loss
goes above that and for my target
specifically for me you can pick how you
want to take targets I normally look
back at previous structure and try to
get something at or above a 1.4 to one
reward to risk ratio as you'll see
whenever I hit play this is a trade we
sent out last week by the way I will put
an image of that right over here so you
can see that I set this trade to EAP and
TTC University members I send these out
two to five times a week if you want to
learn more about that you can follow the
first link in the description or go to
www.ttcfxuniversity.com if not that's
completely fine too but as you can see I
did send this out in what I call email
analysis now directly after sending this
out in email analysis prices did in fact
drop low enough to hit our targets right
here at previous structure and for a
little over a one to one at a 1.4 to 1
reward to risk ratio now let's take a
look at a bullish version of this
pattern if you haven't guessed by now
it's the complete opposite of the
bearish version of this pattern I called
this one the s l e c this stands for
swing low engulfing candle and in this
case we're looking for the same thing we
want to make sure that our Candlestick
pattern is either the swing low of a
trend meaning we're trending down and
it's the lowest candle of the trending
down that we have if that sentence even
makes sense hopefully you understand
what I'm saying other than that it can
be the part it can be a part of a
pullback so we can have prices pushing
higher and then this just needs to
happen at the end of a pullback this
Wick needs to be the lowest Wick of the
pullback of an uptrend that's how it's
going to be classified as a swing low
engulfing candle now ways we can use
this are exactly the same major level of
support something like RSI Divergence
when prices are trending down in order
to capture the reversal of a market or
price is trending higher and using it at
a pullback as we just discussed now
let's go take a look at an example of
this on the charts here on the pound
Swiss chart what has just happened well
hopefully you were able to spot the
reversal in price we have prices that
have been consolidating here not really
putting in new highs and then eventually
we get this push-up pullback and a new
higher high this is our immediate sign
of a possible uptrend starting so in
this case we're looking at an uptrend
and if we go to the swing high right
here what I mean by the swing low of a
pullback is from this swing High looking
at the pullback is going to be the
lowest Scandal that happens throughout
the pullback so here it was this candle
here was this candle these do not count
as the swing low of the pullback
obviously this does count as the swing
low of the pullback so we're waiting on
that to occur the swing low of a
pullback and that candle also be an
engulfing candle so let's see if you can
spot win that happens here on the pound
Swiss As I push prices forward not there
not there not there not quite does that
Candlestick pattern look familiar well
it should because in this case we have
the swing low of a pullback from our
swing high and this candle is also an
engulfing candle so this would be a
valid version of the Swing Low engulfing
candle now in this case we are going to
look at this as a full strategy yet
again using the acronym
c e s t the main things I like to use as
conditions are areas of value and some
indicators the areas of value I like the
most are major levels of structure and
moving averages and on top of that I
really like RSI Divergence as well those
are probably a part of 90 of the trading
opportunities that I take is those three
indications major structure moving
averages and the RSI indicator doing
some type of Divergence along with a
Candlestick pattern or chart pattern
like you're learning in this video so
for the conditions of this specific
trade what do we have
we have prices pulling back to a major
level of structure so I'm going to count
that as condition number one check we
have prices at an area of value being
this moving average this moving average
is the 50 EMA so we have two different
conditions met and if you wanted to turn
this into an entire strategy then what
you could say is I need at least two
conditions say you use structure like
this area of resistance that now could
possibly become support like a moving
average as an area of value whichever
one you want to use and you tell
yourself I need to see at least two
conditions before looking for a possible
entry now what could that entry be
obviously for the scope of this video
because that's what you're learning it
could be the swing low engulfing candle
right here now how would we set this up
well c and e are now covered we need to
find a place for our stop and our Target
before we ever press the buy button so
let's do that go and put a position tool
on the chart stop loss is going to go
under our swing low of this candle and
again my target that structure slash
about a 1.4 to 1 is what I normally use
if we click play you'll see that prices
did in fact push up and hit that quite
easily now just because I know for a
fact there's going to be a few people in
the comments section that try this three
times and lose all three times and then
just go through the comment section
yelling that it doesn't work at all
because of those three attempts let me
explain to you how trading actually
works that way you don't fall into that
trap if you don't have a full trading
plan right now you do not need to trade
this if you do not follow the steps I'm
about to tell you even if you know this
exact Candlestick pattern and the full
strategy we've discussed with cesd
throughout this video even with knowing
that information you will lose money if
you do not listen to the steps I'm about
to tell you
in order to be a professional Trader and
actually make money in any Financial
Market you will not only need a
Candlestick pattern you will not only
need
strategies you're going to need a
strategy that makes money over time
you're going to need a risk management
plan that keeps you emotionless and
you're going to need the trading
psychology in order to stay disciplined
to those two things so knowing a
strategy and knowing an effective
Candlestick pattern is not the secret
it's not the Holy Grail having good risk
management with no strategy equals
losing money as well and you could have
a good risk management plan and a good
strategy but not have any trading
psychology and never stay disciplined to
those two things then you would still
lose money you need a combination of all
three of these things think about it
like gambling and a casino why do
casinos make money a casino is not a
non-profit organization they exist
because that business makes loads of
money how does the casino do it the
casino does this by having a small
advantage over the player in every
single game on the floor every game in a
casino has a slight advantage over
anyone that walks in and gambles what we
do with all three of these is we create
a full trading plan that switches the
script we create a full trading plan
with a strategy that's proven to give us
the edge a risk management plan that
keeps us out of our emotions keeps us
from making these emotional mistakes
like switching strategies and moving our
stop loss and moving our Target and the
trading psychology and discipline to
stick to all of that gives us a slight
Advantage switches the script and turns
us into the casino for that reason if we
can Master these three skills a strategy
that makes money over time a risk
management plan that keeps you out of
your emotions and trading psychology and
or the discipline to stick to those
things then you inevitably become the
casino in over a long period of time
you're the one with the advantage you're
the one coming away making money
otherwise if you do not follow the steps
to create a full trading plan and you
decide to go out here and just randomly
trade this Candlestick pattern I can
nearly get guarantee you you will lose
money because at that point You're Still
The Gambler walking into the casino the
market is the casino until you create an
effective trading plan that gives you an
edge over it so let's talk about
practical steps for a strategy you need
to learn or create a rules-based
strategy I like using the acronym CEST
because it helps keep me consistent I
have conditions entries stops and
targets for every trade I place this not
only keeps me consistent it gives me the
ability to back test and validate this
strategy I can take a look at all these
rules through historic data and I can
back test them that's what that is take
a look at every time this this
rules-based strategy happened and I can
see has it provided an edge in the past
is it something that's proven to make
money if the answer is yes then I now
have a strategy that's proven to make
money in terms of risk management this
is something that's completely up to the
trader some Traders have a very high
risk tolerance some have a very low one
you need to determine what amount of
money what percent of your account can
you stand to lose without becoming
extremely emotional on specific trades
on one specific trade what is that
number a lot of Traders choose two
percent that might be too high it might
be too low but this is about the average
of what retail professional traders that
are again professional and profitable
tend to use it's something between one
percent and two percent of their account
value that they have at risk on a
particular trade as in they have a set
stop loss and the amount of money
they're going to lose on that stop loss
it's normally between one percent and
two percent of their total account value
and again this is something you'll need
to decide for yourself in terms of
trading psychology back testing having a
good risk management plan will help a
lot with your trading psychology
understanding that trading is about a
statistic Advantage will help as well
and reading a ton of books listening to
a lot of videos of Mark Douglas is
something else that really helped me
with my trading psychology at the
beginning of my trading career if you go
watch any videos from Mark Douglas or
read any of his books you'll see a lot
of similarities in the way I speak about
trading psychology and in what he
teaches the main reason for that is I
count him as my main Mentor that taught
me how to have good trading psychology
and discipline and be okay and have a
good trading mindset in my own personal
trading so go take those actionable
steps and if you want some help taking
these steps then of course we do have
some space available in the TTC Forex
University you can get there by the top
Link in the description or by going to
www.ttcfxuniversity.com if that's not
something you're interested in that's
completely fine too be sure you're
subscribed here like the video if you
made it to the end comment if you made
it to the end and I will like every
comment that says they made it to the
end I wish you the best of luck on your
future trades it's hot here in Georgia
so I'm gonna go hit the pool and I'll
see you in the next video talk soon